Guide to the William Nevin Armstrong Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
William Nevins Armstrong papers
1869-1929
1869-1906
MS 39
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
9.5
(13 boxes, 1 folio)
Businessman, diplomat. Correspondence, journals, notes, photographs, clippings, memorabilia and printed matter almost all relating to his trip around the world with King Kalakaua of Hawaii in 1881. Included is a typescript of his Around the World With a King published in 1904. His career as a chairman of the Hawaiian Labor Commission and advisor to the government between 1893 and 1903, when he returned to Washington, is documented in his journals. These form a complete sequence from 1886 to 1905. The large number of photographs record the trip around the world pictorially and also contain views of Hawaii around the turn of the century.
Armstrong, William N.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. Bess Armstrong Howes, 1968.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
William Nevins Armstrong, 1835–1905
1858
William Nevins Armstrong, son of Rev. Richard Armstrong, D.D. (Dickinson 1827), missionary in the Hawaiian Islands, was born in Honolulu, March 10, 1835, but received his early education in Phillips (Andover) Academy. His mother was Clarissa (Chapman) Armstrong.
After graduation he studied law in Springfield, Massachusetts, under his uncle, Chief Justice Chapman, was admitted to the bar in New York in May 1859 and for six and a half years practiced there as a member of the firm of Wheeler & Armstrong. After this he engaged in a number of manufacturing and other enterprises until October 1880, when he accepted the invitations of his former playmate, King Kalakaua, to become Attorney-General of the Hawaiian Islands. Shortly after reaching there, he accompanied the king as "Minister of State" in his ten months trip around the world, meeting emperors, kings, and other rulers, and having many unique experiences. As a result of this trip he published in 1904 the volume, Around the World with a King.
Upon his return to the Hawaiian Islands, he added to his duties as Attorney-General that of Minister of the Interior, and in filling the two offices, met novel questions and puzzling situations. After six months he resigned, but in 1893 returned to Honolulu for his health, and in 1894 became editor of the Commercial Advertiser and Hawaiian Gazette. He was also chairman of the Hawaiian Government Labor Commission, and in the interest of the commission visited Japan in the summer of 1895. He took part in the formation of the Republic and usually attended the Cabinet meetings, as "the adviser of the government." He was a member of the Order of the Rising Sun of Japan, conferred upon him by the Emperor of Japan and entitling him to an audience with the Emperor once a year and to a military funeral. He also received orders commensurate with his rank from Siam, Portugal, and the Kingdom of Hawaii.
Since 1903 he had resided in Washington, D.C., where he died of catarrh of the liver at the Garfield Hospital, October 15, 1905, at the age of 70 years. He was buried in the Island of Hawaii.
He married in New York City, April 10, 1867, Mary Frances, daughter of Captain Elisha Ely Morgan. She was also a sister of his classmate, William Dare Morgan, and of Charles Leslie Morgan (Yale 1867). They had three sons, of whom the second and third sons were graduates of the Sheffield Scientific School in 1895 and 1901 respectively, and a daughter. Mr. Armstrong was a brother of General Samuel Chapman Armstrong (Williams 1862), founder of Hampton Normal and Agricultural Institute.
Scope and Contents
Businessman, diplomat. Correspondence, journals, notes, photographs, clippings, memorabilia and printed matter almost all relating to his trip around the world with King Kalakaua of Hawaii in 1881. Included is a typescript of his Around the World With a King published in 1904. His career as a chairman of the Hawaiian Labor Commission and advisor to the government between 1893 and 1903, when he returned to Washington, is documented in his journals. These form a complete sequence from 1886 to 1905. The large number of photographs record the trip around the world pictorially and also contain views of Hawaii around the turn of the century.
Americans -- Hawaii; Travelers -- United States; Voyages and travels; Asia; Hawaii -- Politics and government -- 1893-1898; Diaries; Businessmen; Diplomats; Lawyers; Armstrong, William N.; Kalakaua, David, King of Hawaii, 1836-1891
- Inventory
  - Correspondence
    - WNA to King Kalakaua, 1880, 1882, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - King Kalakaua to WNA, 1875 - 1890, undated (Box 1, Folder 2 - 3)
    - Miscellaneous official correspondence, 1880 - 1882 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1881 - 1904, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - WNA to Stokes & Co. concerning publication of Around the World with a King, 1903 - 1904 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Stokes & Co. to WNA concerning publication of Around the World with a King, 1903 - 1904 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - L. Thurston to WNA, 1893 December 14, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous items re:
    - Tour with King Kalakaua, 1881, nd. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Around the World with a King, 1903 - 1906, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "Some Notes on Hawaiian Matters" by WNA, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Honors conferred on WNA, 1880 - 1882 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Invitations, clippings, photograph, 1881 - 1892 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Programs, menus, currency, calling card, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Unidentified, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Journals (unbound)
    - Series I and II, 1880 November - 1882 June (Box 2, Folder 16 - 18)
  - MS notes for book, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Journals (bound)
    - Journal, 1886 April - 1890 May (Box 3, Folder 20 - 22)
  - Journal, 1895 June 1 - 16, June 23 - July 6, July 9 - August 9 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Journal, 1895 August - 1896 January 17, March - August (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Journal, 1896 August - 1897 Jul, 1898 January - 1899 Dec, 1902 January - February (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Journal, 1900 February 9 - July 10, 13 - 1902 June (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Journal, 1900 and after (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Journal, 1902 - 1905 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Notebook, undated (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Typescript of journals (728 pp.), 1880 - 1882 (Box 5, Folder 30 - 33)
  - Partial typescript of journals (2nd copy, 267 pp.), 1880 - 1881 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Draft of Around the World with a King (typescript), undated (Box 6, Folder 35 - 36)
  - Printed copy of Around the World with a King, 1904 (Box 6, Folder 37)
  - "Log-Book of the Yacht 'Trabadour'" by [WNA?] (typescript with illustrations), [1887?] (Box 6, Folder 38)
  - "Mr. Someby's Narrative" by an unknown author (mimeograph typescript), undated (Box 6, Folder 39)
  - Calling cards (Box 7, Folder 40)
  - Memorabilia (Box 7, Folder 41)
  - Clippings
    - Obituary of General S.C. Armstrong, 1883 (Box 7, Folder 42)
    - Hawaiian newspapers, 1889 - 1894 (Box 7, Folder 43)
    - Japanese and French newspapers, 1881 (Box 7, Folder 44)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 7, Folder 45)
  - Scrapbook, mostly clippings, with some letters mounted and laid in, 1869 - 1880 (Box 7, Folder 46)
  - Printed matter re:
    - Hawaii (Box 8, Folder 47)
    - Japan (Box 8, Folder 48)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 8, Folder 49)
  - Photographs
    - Photographs of persons of many countries -nobility, celebrities, and ethnic types. (Box 9)
      Scope and Contents
      Consists of 106 collector's photos, 4-1/4 x 6-1/2, mounted on cardboard; 4 collector's photos, 5 x 8-1/2; 18 smaller photos of various sizes, including some personal snapshots.
    - 4 small rough sketches -for placing book illustrations (Box 9)
    - Hawaiian photographs (Box 9)
      Consists of 28 photos of Hawaiian royalty, 9 x 7, on heavy paper; 17 photos unmounted (edges curled and brittle), 7-1/2 x 9-1/4. unidentified agricultural, natural, and urban scenes with ome people; 5 photos mounted on cardboard, 6-1/2 x 9. All marked "H.C.B. 1890": Diamond Head, Woods Near Hilo, In Iao Valley, Surf Riding, and Kamehameha I Statue.
  - Photographs (Oversize)
    - 66 views of people and scenes around the world mounted on cardboard 13 x 17. Pictures vary from ca. 7 x 9 to 8 x 11., undated (Box 10)
  - Photographs (Unusual sizes) and Printed Items
    - View of Hong Kong Harbor (long fold-out picture in seven sections) (Box 11)
    - 3 photographs mounted on 14 x 18 cardboard (Box 11)
      Group shot of luncheon party in Kowloon (with negative) and Palatial home -Hastings St. Luton.
    - Roll of printed illustrations for book: Around the World with a King (4 large sheets: 8 pictures per sheet) (Box 12)
    - 12 separately printed pictures for book (same as those on sheets) (Box 12)
    - Envelope of calling cards (Box 13)
    - Pamphlet (32p.) printed in celebration of Mrs. C.C. Armstrong's 80th birthday, 1885 (Box 13)
    - 19 photographs of people and scenes around the world (approx. 10 x 13 and smaller, some tinted, mounted on cardboard) (Box 13)
    - 16 rolled pictures of Hawaii, some very long (brittle and in poor condition) (Box 14)